<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zigself on sin-ack&#39;s writings</title>
    <link>https://sin-ack.github.io/tags/zigself/</link>
    <description>Recent content in zigself on sin-ack&#39;s writings</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 21:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sin-ack.github.io/tags/zigself/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The inner workings of ZigSelf&#39;s actor model</title>
      <link>https://sin-ack.github.io/posts/zigself-actor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sin-ack.github.io/posts/zigself-actor/</guid>
      <description>Hi there. I wanted to do a series of deep dives about various parts of ZigSelf in order to give others a more thorough explanation of how everything works, and also as a braindump in order to verify my thinking. The first post I wanted to make is regarding ZigSelf&amp;rsquo;s implementation of the actor model, as it&amp;rsquo;s the feature I believe is one of the most interesting aspects of the language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ZigSelf Update, August 2022</title>
      <link>https://sin-ack.github.io/posts/zigself-202208/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sin-ack.github.io/posts/zigself-202208/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi there. It&amp;rsquo;s been quite a while since I posted here, mostly due to real life
responsibilities. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on making monthly updates here from now on so
that I can showcase the new things that are in ZigSelf. For the first update
though, let&amp;rsquo;s play some catch-up.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ZigSelf: An implementation of Self in Zig</title>
      <link>https://sin-ack.github.io/posts/zigself-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sin-ack.github.io/posts/zigself-01/</guid>
      <description>Hello there. I have not posted in a while, and not without good reason. In my first article I had mentioned that I was going to make posts about my own implementation of Self called mySelf. That project never took off, and my interest shifted to other things. I had largely forgotten about it, but then LangJam happened.
LangJam LangJam is a programming jam that works similar to game jams, but instead of developing video games you develop a programming language based around the theme of the jam.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
